<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: linux | Dario's coredump]]></title>
  <link href="http://berdario.github.io/blog/categories/linux/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://berdario.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-08T18:04:59+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://berdario.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Dario Bertini]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The last time I used KDE]]></title>
    <link href="http://berdario.github.io/blog/2014/01/19/the-last-time-i-used-kde/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-19T23:55:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://berdario.github.io/blog/2014/01/19/the-last-time-i-used-kde</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>It happened again: I postponed publishing new posts for months (it&rsquo;s now June when I&rsquo;m publishing this), and I built up a small backlog of things I want to write about. This time it&rsquo;s about KDE: I gathered some of my opinions back in the October of 2011, and after February I got to use it again at work (the workstation ran Nixos and later Fedora, and in both cases KDE seemed like a better choice than modern Gnome), maybe that was the reason for me to postpone this post, anyhow&hellip; on with the impressions that I got in 2011:</em></p>

<p>All of the following is based on Opensuse: it was the very first Linux distribution I ever saw, but after years of Ubuntu I was curious on the current state of Opensuse+KDE.</p>

<p>The first problem was the lack of some packages, but I felt more that the defaults were bothering me more: apparently almost no-one I knew was satisfied with them, and I was disappointed to see that the keyboard shortcuts for very common functions like switching from a workspace to the next, weren&rsquo;t set.</p>

<p>Another issue was the messiness of the desktop, resulting from some of the KDE apps chosing to open new windows instead of opening things in new tabs in the existing windows, like Kopete and Kwrite.</p>

<p>At the time I tried KDE 4.6, which at first glance was better than the 4.4 I tried even earlier: I disliked interacting with Widgets and Activities, but most of all the segfaults in Dolphin and Krunner. KDE 4.6 on comparison was much more stable. The problem with widgets was that I seldom use things that are stuck on desktop, if I have them enabled it&rsquo;s because they supply me some useful information, and for that reason I&rsquo;d like to have them always available on the panel, but the reduced look &amp; feel on the panel was horrible.</p>

<p>Kontact was apparently even slower than Evolution when fetching mail. It required Akonadi, but the weird thing is that by default it wasn&rsquo;t starting up Nepomuk (which was necessary to actually for it to work). The integration with Google in Kontact was also incomplete.</p>

<p>Another issue is the default delay for hot corners: 150ms makes it feel sluggish. Choqok didn&rsquo;t support Facebook and Google Buzz (hey, I was one of its few users at the time :D ). Amarok 2.4&rsquo;s notifications popped up only 3 seconds after the start of the song, and it hid some useful automatic playlists in <code>Media sources -&gt; Dynamic playlists -&gt; Automated playlist generator</code>. Digikam lacked a single-key shortcut to the next photo.</p>

<p>Also (apparently it was supposed to be added in KDE 4.7 but I never tried it out) it was lacking a zoom functionality like the Compiz one, that is: gradual zooming by using the mouse scrollbar. The KDE zoom was only usable with keybindings (which obviously aren&rsquo;t as fluid to use ad quick flick of the scrollbar, if you need just a certain amount of zooming).</p>

<p>Dolphin wasn&rsquo;t hiding bookmarks to volumes that are not currently available (unlike an old version of Gnome&rsquo;s Nautilus, which unfortunately regressed since then &ndash;_&ndash; ).</p>

<p>In a lot of the popups the words are cut off: you have to resize the window or scroll laterally. When you log in, Kwallet isn&rsquo;t unlocked automatically (in Gnome you have to unlock the keyring manually only if you changed the password of one between the keyring or the user to be different than the other). Another cause of concern was the over-reliance on dbus: as I mentioned the system could be quite unstable with segfaults not totally uncommon: well, if dbus failed, the whole system was rendered almost unusable: no launcher, etc. (also other systems have the same weakness, like the global menu in Ubuntu&rsquo;s Unity) but I found it particularly aggravating in KDE.</p>

<p>The <code>.xmodmap</code> file inside your home is not recognized at login, and automatically loaded (another small feature that made my life with Gnome simpler). While it should be possible to do it manually by putting a script inside <code>.kde4/Autostart/</code> I always found the KDE autostart quite unreliable and hard to debug (Like, if the file is not executable or lacks a shebang, it will be opened for editing instead of logging the error).</p>

<p>Unfortunately, this post isn&rsquo;t very structured and I&rsquo;d prefer to accompany each point with a screenshot, but at least this explains why KDE isn&rsquo;t my first choice for a Linux Desktop :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Desktop Setup]]></title>
    <link href="http://berdario.github.io/blog/2012/03/06/My-Desktop-Setup/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-06T15:32:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://berdario.github.io/blog/2012/03/06/My-Desktop-Setup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It took me more time than I expected to write up this second post, I hope to be able to ramp up the rhythm soon.
The reason is that I haven&rsquo;t really wrote this up by impulse&hellip; In fact I wanted to write this since quite some time, and in the meanwhile in the last days, I was busy planning a <a href="http://bglug.it/2012/02/23/bglug-partecipa-allubuntu-global-jam">small Jam</a> along with other small misc duties.</p>

<p>Two years and a half ago I bought a new desktop computer, it had to be shared with my family, so I planned that it would&rsquo;ve run Windows alongside Linux.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s not too bad, since having the opportunity to run games or other software natively on Windows is nice to have, but the truth is that being this only a secondary computer for me, it would&rsquo;ve run Windows most of the time.</p>

<p>So, to test something that I hadn&rsquo;t tried yet at the time (that would&rsquo;ve been useful in case someone dropped by our LUG asking for support about it) and to skip chainloading the Windows bootloader (thus potentially slowing down the boot, something I didn&rsquo;t want: Given that I used an ssd as a boot drive, I wanted to avoid such things, even if it would&rsquo;ve only a marginal effect) I chose to use wubi.</p>

<p>For those that don&rsquo;t know about it: it avoids changing the bootloader with grub and installs ubuntu in a loopback mounted virtual disk (a normal file under windows). It was quite neat, but I stumbled upon some nasty issues when upgrading to grub2, such as <a href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+source/grub2/+bug/477104">this bug</a>.</p>

<p>At the end, I&rsquo;m not quite convinced of the tradeoff in complexity for new users, given the potential nasty edge cases&hellip;</p>

<p>Btw, I also decided to try some other things I didn&rsquo;t really have much experience in linux&hellip; One of these, if I remember correctly, was Ext4; while the other was simply installing Linux on an ATI gpu.</p>

<p>ATI has always had a bad reputation among linux users, but when I chose the hardware for that desktop, the Radeon 4890 seemed like a nice choice, and I was curious about proving that wrong.</p>

<p>In fact, it&rsquo;s been some years now that they started an <a href="http://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=article&amp;item=826&amp;num=1">effort to supply a good OSS driver</a> for their cards. Sure, you can still be out of luck when running a bleeding edge distribution, due to the delay in updating the drivers to get them working with the latest changes in Xorg and such&hellip;</p>

<p>In fact Ubuntu had to <a href="http://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=article&amp;item=amd_open_jaunty&amp;num=1">get into agreements with ATI</a> to be able to ship the drivers in time or <a href="http://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=article&amp;item=ubuntu_1104_radeon&amp;num=1">backport some of the Xorg changes</a>.</p>

<p>Surely, I still found Intel gpu drivers, to be more stable (even if lacking in OpenGL features and performance, and obviously I&rsquo;m not counting the horrible GMA500), but I find it strange that Linux people are still preferring Nvidia over Ati, when they&rsquo;re being so hostile by <a href="http://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=article&amp;item=nvidia_kills_nv&amp;num=1">removing support to their old 2d-only open source driver</a> altogheter without commiting to help the <a href="http://nouveau.freedesktop.org/">Nouveau project</a>.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also seen plenty of times, Linux users with an Nvidia powered laptop, struggling to set up correctly an external display/beamer, this due to the fact that Nvidia doesn&rsquo;t support xrandr1.2 and pushes for their own TwinView option, with their own configuration tools, and their own set of problems.</p>

<p>With this setup, I&rsquo;ve been able to see some interesting things: like the performance of the loopback drive&hellip; by doing a readonly benchmark inside palimpsest I noticed that it was about half of the performance when directly accessing the ntfs drive (that, being a 30GB SSD, is thus really tight for hosting 2 OS installations)</p>

<p>I also chose to keep all the user configuration files on the SSD, and move only huge things on the secondary traditional hard drive&hellip; Thanks to the fact that both Linux and Windows Vista support symbolic links, this gives me quite a bit of flexibility in setting that up. That said, I don&rsquo;t think that the small advantage of being able to load chrome&rsquo;s sqlite dbs faster and such things outweighs the time lost cramming everything into such a small space and tracking down rogue programs/users when those filled their home folder (not to mention the pain of setting up all the symlink for each new user).</p>

<p>In fact I think I won&rsquo;t ever use such a directory layout&hellip; Heck: it&rsquo;s 2012, we aren&rsquo;t supposed to micromanage disk space this way anymore.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
